[Music]
Bluebird Mira I'm really looking forward
to this interview because I watched your
film in shadow and if people are
watching this and haven't seen it I'd
really highly recommend I will put the
link in the show notes for this and
we're gonna probably show some of it on
the screen as we're talking and what I
was really struck by was the the depth
and the breadth of your like it's a
really ambitious project it really kind
of shows what I'd say that the prisons
that we've made for ourselves and the
various traps of kind of modern society
and there is a hopeful kind of ending to
it but I was really struck by just the
depth and the breadth of the vision
which is something I've not seen many
artworks 1/10 let alone pull off in the
way that you managed he managed it and
the first thing to say would be but what
does the film show what's the trajectory
of the film and what how would you
describe it to someone who hasn't seen
it it is a journey through the
unconscious the fractured unconscious of
our cultural psyche at least in the West
but I know that it permeates world
culture overall and that being the in a
way sleepwalking through life
sleepwalking through narratives you know
that we are we we are we're subservient
to but we also
bow down to we we are complicit to these
narratives and we function in a whole
bunch of circuits and programs that are
not of our choosing
and I argue that there if one is not
consciously aware of their actions of
their motivations they are running
closed circuits predictable and
ultimately unsatisfying and destructive
for us all so it's a journey through
that and of course it's it's the the
eventual and inevitable in my opinion
mm-hmm and maybe we'll see that soon the
inevitable breakdown of the illusions
for those who have the fortitude and the
courage to rewire their reality map of
real
and the the consequent infusion what
something rate or something transcendent
which is here for us at all times
embodying that and renewing renewing
this realm and renewing our culture yeah
I mean there's so many questions I'm
looking forward to asking you and when I
was going to talk about later on but I
feel like I'm gonna ask it now is
because I've watched the film like more
than once and it's very intense
there is this this sort of as you say
kind of hopeful transcendent ending to
it but it almost feels like an
afterthought like it's so relentless the
first sort of part of the film
do you and can you explain that like
what is what is the hopeful end to it
after this sort of really kind of
relentless and quite dystopian vision
earlier in the film yeah very good
question and it's a probably the most
difficult question to answer and then
leave it till the end of your that's
cool
yeah it's it is the most difficult
question to answer only because there's
so much so much of the vernacular
connected to this process of awakening
can be there
UAG or cliched or maybe too intellectual
and it's it's a fine
it's a it's a tightrope to walk but in a
way it's it's within I think your field
of inquiry and I think Jordan house in
terms of sovereignty probably applies
very very strongly to this and not
probably it does apply very strongly to
the sovereignty meaning cutting the
strings of influence those are the
influence of our own psyche of our own
upbringing of our programming the coping
patterns mechanisms that we've inherited
that we have taken on as
protected by you know the the child to
though child growing up and then
whatever circumstances represent that
consequently become in the social mask
that being confused for the reality of
the self and the social mask is ten and
in constant competition with the outside
world and costs the protection and in
constant enhancement the curation of its
image and I listened he did a really
interesting interview with a mutual
friend of ours Peter Lindbergh where you
talked about some of this the symbolism
and the imagery in the film and one of
that you talked about kind of waking up
and I didn't really realize until
listening to that interview with Peter
that everyone has their eyes closed
throughout the film right up until the
end could you describe some of the sort
of specific imagery that you use and
what it represents in the film yeah
there overall the film was a fine line
between being accessible enough to a
general audience because I didn't want
to preach to the choir and also
calibrating it for for for truth in a
way without beating people over the
heads you know some of the symbolism
values the symbols are young to suits
that's a cliche way of expressing a
certain certain type of occupation in
our world so I wish I had found a more
elegant way to to describe that but
other symbols are yes the eye is being
closed then I think that works
subconsciously on the psyche of going
through all these individuals who are
whose guys are either and in shadow
presumably closed or are actually closed
and the impact at the end of the film
the mind the two eyes open that can be
profound to some viewers other symbols
are you know the cube the red cube the
six sided cube some some people have
noted there are many synchronistic
alignments to that 6iq
it's that the mask as well the dark
clouds the dark gunk coming out of some
individuals yeah so I guess I can start
with the cube and the cube in a very
broad broad way
speaking as narratives and
interpretations of events of our reality
of a way of being in this world can in
my opinion be traced and there's a
strong argument to be made that many
narratives are manufactured to what end
sometimes we can guess other times we
know to what end the cube itself is a it
can be a binding tool and when placed
over the head symbolically it creates a
filter so that Oh incoming data is
filtered through that cubes structure
and so that's all we receive and that's
all we that's how we act in the world
according to those presets very very
simply saying defining that and then the
mask of course is the social persona
it's the it's as I mentioned earlier
it's it's it's something that's
constructed as a way to buffer the
anxiety of the world the threat of the
world and our misconceptions about it
our distorted perceptions of of its
rules and laws and what we need to be
safe to feel loved to do to either get
love validation all those primal primal
elements required for sustenance and
being here spiritually and emotionally
just mentally and so the mask is this
buffer which which hides my true self
and our true self many times that lower
aspect of us the shadow aspect there's
pain deep deep pain discomfort sadness
all kinds of things that can be masked
by a well curated image and this well
curated image can and there's a scene in
the film in a way which this couple
advertises this on a screen advertises
the mask it comes out to the first first
man it's there are many types of masks
that that are advertised you know
whether it's intentional or not they are
and those masks are available for our
purchase so to speak embodying those
masks
and there are they're extremely limiting
because they're closed circuits they
allow certain types of behavior and they
require a certain kind of feedback they
seek success and that successes am i
validated and they constantly need to be
fed and the other thing that comes to
mind there are that there's a lot of
other symbolism but the other thing
that's a running theme is the dark sort
of cloud that comes through the bodies
and all of these images were were
designed in a way to evoke feelings and
emotions and so the dark cloud itself is
just that it came from my own feeling
emotions of observing and feeling myself
and feeling doubting others and it's
almost as disrupt this purification of
in a repression of disowning the shadow
the summoning that which is deformed it
doesn't work which really is crying out
to be untangled and then brought to bite
so that health vitality and life can
truly flow through and create higher
order so that that dark gunk is the
purification of all that and it it just
indicates heavy suppression of shadow
have your own consciousness obviously
the title refers is called in shadow and
that's a term that maybe people are
familiar with from Jungian psychology
which shadow being all the parts of
ourselves that we don't that we reject
or we don't integrate is that a you is
that where it comes from for you is it a
kind of Jungian reference
it's a Jungian reference but it didn't
come from that originally it's it just
came from Jung tapped into some a
reality right and then he defined it for
us in the 20th century and so it's a
great great a very apt metaphor but it
didn't originally come from Jung though
I love you and I'm very inspired by many
of his articulations of reality and the
way he frames much of the archaic wisdom
and the conscious adventure of become of
becoming conscious from our
consciousness is it's it's a process
it's a slow process
of shining light on things and
integrating them can be very
uncomfortable and so the shadow is
really helps us evolve without it
creates the tension it's it's kind of
like that sharpening rock because we
thought it blade would just stay pretty
dull it asks of us to constantly
reorganize at a higher level and when we
do so I feel the unconsciousness just
catches up or the shadow that's created
matches the new light and that interplay
can be really beautiful however we are
in a way wired biologically and mentally
to avoid discomfort and avoid pain but
it's only in this honest conscious
suffering if you want to say which is
very heroic of going into shadow
understanding it integrating it do we
really evolve so it's like in shadow is
a piece in which you know you said it's
pretty intense well yeah I wanted to
really fling it and to at that point
what I was making it around 2012 is when
I had the idea and that I started in 20
and 15 to actually make it I I felt
there were people around me um who I
felt like you know that the TRO and you
just wanted to throw some things in
their face and be like you have to look
at some things we were just talking
before we started recording and you
mentioned that you basically kind of
locked yourself away throughout the the
making of it like it was very much a
kind of individual project can you tell
me about that why why was that and what
was the experience of making it like I
didn't share the project with anyone I
didn't feel it would be understood and I
the only way I could describe what I was
intending to relay was to finish the
piece then and relay it that way because
it's not a verbal piece it's not an
essay it's not a book it is simply an
experience and it's a barrage of images
it's a tapestry that I was trying to
weave and so in that regard I had to
be within my own space and then way
excavate my own shadow then at work of
that so it's very much a kind of
therapeutic process for you making it
yeah it definitely was therapeutic so it
it exercised a lot of this darkness that
made me feel okay with things as they
are as I see them so that I can continue
having integrated that and move forward
with inner solutions and move forward in
a way with which I could navigate this
world with the full awareness of the
more negative implications of our world
and yet make not make the best of it but
and yet move forward efficiently and
effectively well for myself and the
world
so yeah art art is can be that and
actually should be done it's a it's a
healing process for the artists and the
audience in my opinion and at its best
it should be a pillar of light that
aligns in a way outlines its audience
because we need to be renewed and I
think you will know that that
traditional ceremonies rituals aligning
to the cycles inherent in nature and the
cosmos we fall away from knowing and
being aware of the cycles we don't get
that renewal we don't get that with
verification and so I believe that
truthful art can do that and should aim
to do that is to infuse a transcendent
impulse a transcendent element into our
tendency to sort of like go into
cultural mental entropy in our entropy
we and we do that reveal fiying in
various ways whether it's you know
shopping or promotions and many ways we
tried we needed but I feel that our
spirit our emotions our psyche overall
means that infusion that's sprinkling of
some something higher
yeah and that's suddenly a question I'd
love to ask you because I do get that
sense of the real calling in of the
transcend
in your work and I don't see that so
much in a lot of art nowadays I mean you
can kind of talk about whether art has
become a lot more parochial than its
concerns rather than trying to create
these grand visions but I don't see that
so much like but what do you do you see
much art that is kind of aiming at that
kind of grand vision nowadays yeah well
I don't in to be fair I don't look hard
enough so that's that having said that I
see a lot of art that I work in
animation so of course that's more craft
based very pop culture driven so you
don't don't get deep inquiry in any way
and I find that even the deeper inquiry
of some animations tend to be in a
certain cultural narrative that I find I
find it's popular at the moment but not
very insightful so yeah what the artists
work the true artists work and and you
know that's that's my aim and my good
days is to to calibrate to a higher
order to have inner integrity and so the
artist has to be able to go into the
transcendent realms in various ways and
through the interaction with these
realms through emptying oneself of the
cultural baggage being able to take that
boom like grasp it with gentleness I
think and sometimes with gentle force
and be able to then make sense of it so
it's almost a mystical experience the
insight of the experience has to be felt
then understood then put into some sort
of human manifestation so that it can be
translated to others and then put into
putting to craft that can then be that
stream can be felt by human beings who
are functioning within these closed
circuits that's just what we we tend to
do so the artists it's it's a lot to ask
because true art has to be done by by
the initiates of the true work the real
work
and that work is not easy and it's not
promoted anywhere and it's not mmm
it's it's not part of our culture to do
that that work so we need we need more
artists to be doing really hard work
working on their craft and translating
the transcendent and introducing a
higher order of reality so that the rest
of us can can glean it consider it and
possibly even you know take it on and
embody it yeah I mean it feels like the
narrative lie aren't used to be
intrinsically tied to religious feeling
to calling in the transcendent calling
into like really the higher aspects of
our nature and it feels like especially
with post-modernism the idea of any kind
of grand narrative or anything to reach
for beyond this world it sort of is
considered naive so I guess what what
you're saying is that we need to
rekindle that sort of sense of something
bigger something beyond ourselves yeah
and there's there was a necessity in my
opinion and definitely the things that
are the things that happen in the art
world in the 20th century were necessary
and I think it was a necessary cleansing
of the palette in a way but I think it
turned it creator psychosis in the art
world and then that aligned into the
social media culture the scenester
aspect the the not enough Nestor needs
to be filled by status and a lot of
artists just like our creators all
perfectly well mostly they just keep it
to creators
there's a status game in a race upward
to some sort of you know satisfaction
which never will come sorry but you know
so it's that while that was necessary in
post-modernism etcetera I think people
are just a bit too fixated now into the
this like you know just being a bit too
cool which is unfortunate that's quite a
bondage and quite a trap
not to be able to feel deeply into
something and I'm definitely of the
opinion and the feeling in the sense
that I can truly appreciate more and
more tradition when I book it into I
consider it take it in and also deeply
can appreciate the need
challenged tradition to elevate it and
to keep restructuring and so that it's
available and apt for our time and for
our situations and and this polarity of
like either-or that you know our culture
keeps going into sometimes being is
being steered into it's much more easily
manageable that way but we're just
creatures of we want a final answer and
final certainty so yeah it's not about
full tradition
it's not about full dismantling of
things it's it's it's a mix of the two
you got to be rebellious while knowing
what you're stepping onto and you're
stepping on to the efforts of so many
men and women that have brought us here
you know the fabrics that we wear the
walls they're like these things we we
live on the you know the shoulders of
giants and I think there should be a lot
of gratitude for that while also
innovating constantly so we have to be
at the razor edge of reality right here
right now aware of it all were also
aware of our own sense yeah and you
mentioned sort of the the the the trap
of cool within within the art world and
that also sort of links up for me with
cynicism it's like it's much easier if
you're cynical if you're producing
something that's quite cynical then it's
very hard to be sort of ridiculed or
criticized for that it's when you
actually reach for the grand visions and
the grand sort of potentials that then
you kind of open yourself out to being
criticized or opening yourself up to
being made fun of so it's yeah putting
forward such a kind of compelling
potential kind of awakening vision as
well kind of the idea of awakening it
sort of can be seen as so cliched or so
new-age or so kind of 1960s well that's
from the past so actually putting that
out as an act of bravery it feels like
mm-hmm
thank you yeah it's funny that the Asian
saying of the nail that sticks out gets
hammered down like it's just so true and
and all spheres of society the high
intellectual realms and the so-called
sophisticated realms you know one has to
maintain a tailored image of oneself and
I know that there are functions for that
you know I have to do it in certain
instances and I'm trying now to do it as
much but that keeps us that that
coolness you know that that just keeps
us limited to
- again if I keep saying this but a
closed circuit a certain groove that we
chose oh and and then we become binded
to that and we can't escape it so yeah
thank you for for the compliment of
bravery my experience of it was I I
didn't face too much inner resistance to
releasing it so I would say you know
true courage comes when there's in the
face of a lot of fears so I didn't face
too much fear and releasing it I did of
course you know anticipate some ridicule
and and all sorts of claims of being
unsophisticated and etc etc but I felt
this was I wanted to do this I felt that
it was okay to throw my hat out and be
like yeah yeah here are some things I
stand for when I released the film I I
had grown past many of the things not
past but I had grown a sophistication in
the way that I understood many of the
things I elaborated in the film and so
of course I wanted that to be to be
recognised perhaps and but but I also
saw that there's a there's value in the
film as it was for for for people who
are on the ladder of coram quote
awakening or just reorganizing their or
claiming the sovereignty of their own
decision-making and interpretation of
the world because what is awakening
awaken and I think is this signpost
catch-all term that a lot of people you
know it's a god lot of people can
project all kinds of things into and
just wave it off but Awakening is it's
it's I mean it's all there is what else
is there but to climb the ladder of
conscious realization and integration of
more and more sense data and being
present with it and seeing it as it is
and creating our own world through our
perceptions but I just don't see
anything more noble than that because
it's only through that that we can act
rightfully into the world that we can
imprint ourselves into the world in a
way that truly matters and that helps
this whole ecosystem of consciousness
grow you know I'd love to ask what you
have made of the reception to the film I
think it's got it's got over 2 million
views on YouTube families and
- now yeah I believe it's two million
you know it's on Vimeo and people have
been posting it on Facebook it has its
own so it's taken off from there in
other ways as well
what have you made of the reception to
it so far I I don't think I've I've I've
taken as much pleasure as I could have
out of it I wasn't sure what to make of
it my correspondence is what there's
been a lot of correspondence with with
viewers getting in touch some of their
some of their thoughts and views on the
film have been quite staggering
magnificent and have given me a lot of
insight it's I'm glad to say that the
film has had a real-life impact in some
people so the experiment worked
now I know that the recipe can be
refined and moving forward and so what
have I made of it is that people are
clearly hungry for some sort of
recognition that things are not okay in
a certain way what aspects of the world
may not be okay and really to to feel
that there is something beyond it that
you know in the grand scheme of things
this is in a way a game it gave a game
of restructuring integrating and and
that need as there's a yeah I you know a
big question that comes up as one is the
next one coming up or what what my next
artworks will be and of course that's
very understandable so there is an
element of just consuming mindlessly
though within that and um not taking it
in but I think people are are hungry for
real visceral experiences that touch
them beyond the intellect so you you've
made the film and sent it out there what
were you hoping to get from that and
what do you hope people will get from
the film and well my hope was for people
who are not who take reality as it's
given to them as its curated for them
and for them to be jarred out of it at
least a little bit for at least some
seeds to be planted and that can
germinate into more inquiry
into you know the images of the film in
the film itself I was hoping would
recontextualize some of the
relationships that we take for granted
between institutions and ourselves and
the greater social framework so my hope
was mostly for the people who may be
quite caught up with in their habitual
patterns to be really like to chart out
of that with a strong punch to the solar
plexus to get their own will out there
moving into the world yeah I guess one
one comment I I have I sent it out to my
email list to receive people's responses
to it and one comment that came back was
that is there a danger in seeing I guess
there's a question to you as well like
that that there's a lot of sort of kind
of almost like puppet-masters energy in
the film sort of behind behind people
who are speaking there's there's moneyed
interests do you see it as a group of
people or do you see it as sort of the
strange attractors of money and power
because I I'm I I personally I would see
it more as the latter kind of that there
are that there are they have their own
force that money in power has its own
corrupting influence on these things not
so much that there's sort of a hidden
puppet masters kind of energy to it yeah
yeah I mean I I would go I would say
both and I'll go into that I think the
ecosystem of power control is is complex
and I'm not sure anyone's done a great
great intricate job in explaining it and
diving deep into it because a lot of the
intellectual sphere
looks down upon your alternate theories
that maybe a bit too far away from you
know what's deemed acceptable within
their spheres when I find that
unfortunately that really impedes
progress and and excavating the reality
of the situation
I do see uninvested a certain
concentrated interest with certain goals
certain outcomes steadily at the very
least about the 20th century you know
for that sort of for that to really sink
in
there are leaked think-tank papers there
there are a lot of legitimate resources
out there which can really show us the
intentions and a coherent shaping of
society in a certain way in a certain
direction now I don't like blaming those
powers I just want to recognize that
they are there and that I believe I
their unconscious to a large degree I
feel that they're running many programs
and in a way it's their imperative once
they connected to the momentum of their
in-group I believe that these yeah these
sort of tendencies get propagated a kind
of ongoing question for us but we've
kind of been kind of playing with quite
a while is where are the artists as a
sort of question because there does seem
to be a sort of an emerging cultural
movement or at least a sort of a set of
people who are asking similar questions
who are sort of asking these deeper
questions about reality but the jordan
green halls or the daniel Shmack tim
burgers or some of these people with
very sort of big visions for game a
being the society that we've got now and
that's kind of coming to the end of life
and then game B being something that is
emergent we don't really know what it
looks like but it certainly seems to
have elements of authentic dialogue of
inter subjective collective intelligence
of all of these different factors and
we're sort of saying okay see if this is
a thing then where are normally cultural
movements are driven by art they're
driven by the outliers of the artists
and I'm not really seeing so many people
dealing with those questions I'd say
that you you definitely are are one of
them
do you have any thoughts about that like
where are the artists in this space yeah
well I think true artists disincentivize
so the art world leans in a certain
direction and it's within the you know
the dictates of the Empire and the
Empire controls art controls fill it
controls media it's just the way it is
this is why we see synchronized there
pop-up to define any situation for us
and that has to be challenged any
challenges to the to the top-down
narrative that's being imposed by
artists those artists get the platform
and deeply disincentivized and
discouraged from going forward so where
are the artists I feel there are a lot
of artists that are capable and willing
but to create our keynote requires
personal discipline fortitude and and
vision and and staying power with it you
know like no production no no no
procrastination it means building
character and and there needs to be
encouragement and rewards for that that
work it's exhausting and it's it's very
taxing and if there is no reward than
even in the form of a tap on the back
and saying thank you like you brought
something it may be wrong it may not be
you know the right it's in the right
direction and you you risked to do it
and so yeah the things that I feel like
I could do now I can't quite do because
of other things happening with me quote
unquote career-wise that may
strategically in the future yield the
greater benefit for a game for the whole
so we'll see about that
but I think there's there's fear in the
atmosphere so artists do need to be
courageous right now and I think they
really need to be supported but we have
we have many artists thematic Wars or
you know our rife with Mike all kinds of
geniuses in my opinion and that digital
magic the digital spells are being cast
constantly they rewired consciousness
and they create new connections and new
relations to to to our reality so it's
almost like art now is more a guerrilla
warfare it's not this establishment
authorized stamped and approved
Hollywood film the January comedy or you
know whatever it is some sort of
Pentagon a war a narrative but yeah I
don't know just even just saying that's
relating to this to you I feel an
emerging sense that yeah the artists
actually are there it's just that
they're not gonna come out with their
flag and be like I am here I think that
are emerging and you know as the old
guard crumbles and I'm starting to see
the beginning a beginning of that yeah
we'll see and I guess the question a lot
of people who enjoyed the film will be
asking is is there a sequel gonna happen
is that what happens next
yeah well what happens next I think will
have to happen in the real world what
happens next for me as of a few things
in the can I'm working on something
professionally they're just honing my
craft right now beyond that I am writing
something and we'll see it's I think
it's something more involved and
something I think more powerful and if
the right if the right forces come
together my inner and outer forces I
will manifest itself if not that's okay
too well done for making it to the end
just wanted to let you know a few things
we've got coming up including the
biggest event we've ever done the rebel
wisdom festival which will be a mix of
ideas and dialogues between people like
Daniel Shmack Tim burger Bonita Roy
Rupert Sheldrake John Devaki and many
more and because wisdom isn't just
intellectual it's also about practice
will be offering experiences like
circling different interpersonal
dialogue mindfulness breath work and
many other with world-class facilitators
and if you're enjoying the content you
can help us make more by joining the
rebel wisdom club which will give you
discounts and the courses and the events
and also access to a load more content
on the website including all of our live
events it'll also give you access to our
growing community which is something
want to make a real focus for 2020
adding more meetups and other services
for members so I hope you enjoyed the
film and see you soon